<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Touching the fundamentall lawes, or politique constitution of this kingdome, the Kings negative voice, and the power of Parliaments. To which is annexed the priviledge and power of the Parliament touching the militia.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E90_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871402</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871402</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E90[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Touching the fundamentall lawes, or politique constitution of this kingdome, the Kings negative voice, and the power of Parliaments. To which is annexed the priviledge and power of the Parliament touching the militia.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, 10-13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Underhill, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIII. [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 24 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Militia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Touching the Fundamentall Lawes, Or Politique Conſtitution of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, The KINGS Negative Voice, and The Power of PARLIAMENTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is annexed,</hi> The priviledge and power of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment touching The MILITIA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Bible in Woodſtreet. <hi>M.DC.XLIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:123813:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123813:2"/>
            <head>TOUCHING FVNDAMENTALL LAVVS, <hi>AND</hi> The KINGS Negative Voice.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Vndamentall Laws are not (or at leaſt néed not be) any written agréement like Meare-ſtones betwéen King and People, the King himſelfe being a part (not party) in thoſe Laws, and the Common-wealth not being like a Corporation treated by Charter, but treating it ſelfe. But the fundamentall Law or Laws is a ſetling of the laws of nature and common equity (by common conſent) in ſuch a forme of Polity and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that they may be adminiſtred amongſt us with honour and ſafety. For the firſt of which therefore, we are governed by a King: and for the ſecond, by a Parliament, to overſée and take order that that honourable truſt that is put into the hands of the King for the dignity of the Kingdome, be rightly executed, and not abuſed to the alteration of the Politique Conſtitution taken up and approved, or to the deſtruction of that, for whoſe preſervation it was ordered and intended. A principall part of which honour, is that royall aſſent he is to give for the enacting of ſuch good Laws as the people ſhal chooſe, for they are firſt to conſult their own ſafety and welfare, and then he who is to be intruſted with it, is to give an honourable confirmation to it, and ſo to put an Impreſſe of Majeſty and Royall authority upon it.</p>
            <p>Fundamentall Laws then are not things of capitulation between King and people, as if they were Forrainers and Strangers one to another, (nor ought they or any other Laws ſo to be, for then the King ſhould governe for himſelfe, not for his people) but they are things of conſtitution, treating ſuch a relation, and giving ſuch an exiſtence and being by an externall polity to King and Subjects, as Head and Members, which conſtitution in the very being of it is a Law held
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123813:3"/>forth with more evidence, and written in the very heart of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, ſarre firmlyer then can be by pen and paper, and in which ſenſe we owe our Allegiance to the King as Head, (not onely by power, but in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uence) and ſo part of the conſtitution, not as a party capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating for a prerogative againſt or contrary to it, which whoſoever ſeeks to ſet up, or ſide with, doe break their Allegiance, and rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State, going about to deprive the King of his juridicall and lawfull authority, conferred upon him by the conſtitution of this State, under the pretence of inveſting him with an illegall and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtitutive power, whereupon may follow this grand inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, The withdrawment of His peoples Allegiance, which, as a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy connexed with the Head by the conſtitution of this Kingdome, is owing to him; his perſon in relation to the body, as the enlivening and quickning head thereof, being ſacred and taken notice of by the laws in that capacity, and under that notion is made inviolate.</p>
            <p>And if it be conceived that Fundamentall Laws muſt néeds be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extant in writing, this is the next way to bring all to confuſion, for then by the ſame rule the King bids the Parliament produce thoſe Laws that fundamentally give them their being, priviledges &amp; power, <hi>(Which by the way is not like the power of inferiour Courts, that are ſprings of the Parliament, dealing betweene party and party, but is anſwerable to their truſt, this Court being it ſelfe Fundamentall and Paramount, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Law and Equity, and being intruſted by the whole for the whole, is not therefore to be circumſcribed by any other Laws which have their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, not it from them, but onely by that Law which at firſt gave it its being, to wit, <hi>Salus populi</hi>)</hi> By the ſame rule I ſay the Parliament may alſo intreat the King to produce thoſe Laws that Fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give him his being, power and honour. Both which muſt therefore be determined, not by laws, for they themſelves are laws, yea the moſt ſupreame and fundamentall law, giving law to laws themſelves, but by the received conſtitution or policy, which they themſelves are; and the end of their conſtitution is the law or rule of their power, to wit, An honourable and ſafe Regiment of the Common-wealth, which two whoſoever goeth about to divide the one of them from the other, breaks the fundamentall conſtitutive law or laws polity of this kingdome, that ordinance of man which we are to ſubmit unto; nor can or ought any ſtatute or written law whatſoever, which is of later Edition and inferiour Condition, being but an off-ſpring of this root, be interpreted or brought in Plea, againſt this primary and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall conſtitution, without guilt of the higheſt Treaſon and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123813:3"/>enmity to the Publique weale and polity, becauſe by the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtitution of this Kingdome, all laws or interpretation of laws ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to confuſion or diſſolution, are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void. In this caſe we may allude and ſay, That the Covenant which was <hi>400.</hi> yéers before the Law, an after-Act cannot diſanull it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It may be objected, that this diſcourſe ſéems to make our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be founded in Equity, not in Law, or upon that common rule of <hi>Salus populi,</hi> which is alike common to all Nations, as well as any: and ſo what difference:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Fundamentall laws of England are nothing but the Common laws of Equity and Nature reduced into a particular way of policy, which policy is the ground of our title to them, and intereſt in them: For though it is true, that Nature hath inveſted all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in an equall right to the laws of Nature and Equity by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bounty, without reſpect of perſons, yet the ſeverall models of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Government and Policie renders them more or leſſe capable of this their common right: For though they have an equall right in Nature to all the Laws of Nature and Equity, yet having funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally ſubjected themſelves by their politique Conſtitutions unto a Regal ſervitude, by Barbariſme or the like, they have thereby much diſabled and diſveſted themſelves of that common benefit. But on the contrary, where the outward conſtitution or polity of a Republick is purpoſely framed for the confirming and better conſerving this common right of Nature and Equity, (as in ours) there is not onely a common right, but alſo a particular and lawfull power joyned with this right for its maintenance and ſupportion. For whereas other people are without all ſupreame power, either of making laws or rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing monies, both theſe bodies of ſupremacie being in the arbitrary hands onely of the Soveraigne Magiſtrate amongſt many Nations, theſe with us are in the hands of the ſupreame Government, (not Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour) or Court of Iudicature, to wit, the King and Parliament; here the people (like Frée-men) give money to the King, he doth not take it; and offers Laws to be enacted, doth not receive them ſo: Now in ſuch a conſtituted Kingdome, where the very Conſtitution its ſelfe is the fundamentall law of its owne preſervation, as is this mixt Regiment of ours, conſiſting of King and Parliament, as Head and Body, comprehending Monarchie, Ariſtocracie, and Democracie; there the fundamentall laws are like fundamentall truths in theſe two properties: Firſt, they are comprehended in a very little room, to wit, honour and ſafety; and ſecondly, they have their influence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123813:4"/>to all other inferiour Laws which are to be ſubjected to them, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent with them, as lawful children and naturall branches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But in proceſſe of time there are many written Laws which ſéem at leaſt to contradict this Fundamentall Conſtitution, and are not they binding notwithſtanding it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Conſtitution of this Kingdome which gave it its being, and which is the radicall and fundamentall law thereof, ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to command in chiefe, for that it never yéelds up its authority to thoſe inferiour laws, which have their being from it, nor ought they which ſpring from it tend to the deſtruction of it, but on the contrary, it is to derive its radicall virtue and influence into all ſuccéeding laws, and they like branches are to make the root flouriſh, from whence they ſpring, with exhibiting the lively and ſtructifying virtue thereof, according to the nature and ſeaſons of ſuccéeding times; things inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in after-ages not being able to be fore-ſeen, and particularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for at the beginning, ſaving in the fundamentall law of <hi>Salus populi,</hi> politiquely eſtabliſhed; nor can any laws growing out of that root, bear any other fruit, then ſuch as the nature thereof dictates; for, for a particular branch to ruine the whole foundation by a ſéeming ſenſe contrary to it, or differing from it, is very abſurd; for then how can it be ſaid, Thou beareſt not the root, but the root thée? Laws muſt alwayes reliſh of, and drink in the conſtitution or polity where they are made; and therefore with us, the laws wherein the King is nominated, and ſo ſéems to put an abſolute authority into his hands, muſt never ſo be conſtrued, for that were with a breath to blow downe all the building at once; but the King is there comprehended and meant under a two-fold notion; Firſt, as truſted, being the Head, with that power the Law conferd upon him, for a Legall, and not an abſolute purpoſe, tending to an honourable preſervation, not an unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diſſolution. Secondly, as meaning him juridically, not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly or perſonally, for ſo onely the Law takes notice of the King as a juridicall perſon: for till the Legiſlative power be abſolutely in the King, ſo that laws come down from him to his people, and goe not up from them to him, they muſt ever be ſo interpreted: for as they have a juridicall being and beginning, to wit, in Parliament, ſo muſt they have a ſutable execution and adminiſtration, to wit, by the Courts, and legall Miniſters, under the Kings authority, which according to the conſtitution of this Kingdome, he can no more ſuſpend for the good of his people, then the Courts can theirs; or if he doe, to the publique hazard, then have the Courts this advantage, that for publique preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123813:4"/>they may and muſt provide upon that principle, <hi>The King can doe no wrong, neither in withholding juſtice, nor protection from his people.</hi> So that then <hi>Salus populi</hi> being ſo principally reſpected and provided for, according to the nature of our conſtitution and polity, &amp; ſo being <hi>Lex legum,</hi> or the rule of all laws branching thence, Then if any law doe by variation of times, violence of tyrannie, or miſpriſion of Interpreters, vary there-from, it is a baſtard, and not a ſon, and is by the lawful parents either to be reduced or caſt out, as gendring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage and ruine of the inheritance, by attempting to erect an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and arbitrary Government. Nor can this equitable expoſition of particular Statutes taken from the ſcope of the politique conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be denyed without overthrow of juſt and legal Monarchy, (which ever tends to publique good and preſervation) and the ſetting up of an unjuſt and illegall tyrannie, ruling, if not without law, yet by abuſed laws, turning them as conquered ordnance upon the people. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Scripture it ſelfe muſt borrow from its ſcope and principles for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of particular places, elſe it will be abuſed (as it is through that default) unto Hereſies. Sée we not how falſely Satan quoted true Scripture to Chriſt when he tempted him, onely by urging the letter without the equity, or true intention and meaning? We are to know and doe things <hi>verum verè, juſtum juſtè,</hi> else we neither judge with righteous judgement, nor obey with juſt obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But is not the Parliament guilty of exerciſing an arbitrary power, if their procéedings be not regulated by written laws, but by <hi>Salus populi?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the Parliament to be bound up by written laws, is both deſtructive and abſurd.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is deſtructive, it being the Fundamental Court and Law, or the very <hi>Salus populi</hi> of England, and ordained, as to make laws, and ſée them executed, ſo to ſupply their deficiencie according to the preſent exigencie of things for publique preſervation by the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of <hi>Salus populi,</hi> which is univerſally in them, and but particularly in particular laws and ſtatutes, which cannot provide againſt all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture exigents, which the law of Parliaments doth, and therefore are not they to be limits to this. And it would yet be further deſtructive, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utting the Parliament ſhort of half its power at once, for it being a Court both of Law and Equity (as appears by the power of making laws, which is nothing but Equity reduced by common conſent into Polity) when ever it is ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cumſeribed by written laws, (which onely is the property of inferiour Courts) it ceaſeth to be ſupreame, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123813:5"/>it ſelfe of that inherent and uncircumſeribed power which <hi>Salus populi</hi> comprehends.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it is deſtructive, ſo alſo it is abſurd; for the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power which gives laws, is not to receive laws, ſaving from the nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re and end of its owne conſtitution, which as they give it a being, ſo they endow it with l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ws of preſervation both of it ſelfe &amp; the whole, which it repreſents.</p>
            <p>I would not herein be miſ-underſtood, as if the Parliament, when as it onely doth the office of inferiour Courts, judging between party &amp; party, were not limited by written lawes: there I grant it is, becauſe therein it only deales between <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> which particular writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten lawes, can and ought to determin: ſo that its ſuperlative and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumſeribed power I intend only as relating to the Univerſe and the affaires thereof, wherein it is to walke by its fundamentall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, not by particular precepts or Statutes, which are made by the Parliament, betwéen King and people, not betwéen people and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: they are ordayned to be rules of Government to the King, agreeing with the liberty and property of the people, and rules of Obedience to the people without detainment of their freedome by the exerciſe of an illegall, uſurped, and unconſented power, whereunto Kings (eſpecially in hereditary Monarchies) are very prone, which cannot be ſuſpected by a Parliament, which is repreſentatively the Publike, intruſted for it, &amp; which is like to partake and ſhare with the Publick, being but ſo many private men put into authority <hi>protempore,</hi> by common conſent, for common good.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Parliament hereby guilty of an Arbitrary Government, or is it deſtructive to the Petition of Right, when as in providing for publick weale, it obſerves not the letter of the law; firſt, becauſe as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, that law was not made betwéene Parliament and people, but by the people in Parliament betwéene the King and them, as appears by the whole ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur of it, both in the complaining and praying parts, which wholly relate to the King. Secondly, becauſe of the common conſent, that in the repreſentative Body (the Parliament) is given thereunto, wherein England in her Polity imitates Nature in her Inſtincts, who is wont to violate particular principles for publique preſervation, as when light things deſcend, and heavy aſcend, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a <hi>vacuum:</hi> and thirdly, becauſe of the equitable power which is inherent in a Parliament, and for publique good is to be acted above and againſt any particular Statute, or all of them: and fourthly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the end of making that Law, to wit, the publique preſervation,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123813:5"/>is ſulfild in the breaking of it, which is lawfull in a Parliament that is choſen by the whole for the whole, and are themſelves alſo of the body, though not in a king, for therein the Law ſaith, Better a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife then an inconuenience. But it may be objected, though it be not Arbitrary for the Parliament to goe againſt written law, yet is it not ſo when they go againſt the Kings conſent, which the law, even the fundamentall law, ſuppoſeth in Parliamentary proceedings; This hath beene anſwered, that the King is juridically and according to the intention of the law in his Courts, ſo that what the Parliament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults for the publick good, That by oath, and the duty of his office, and nature of this polity he is to conſent unto, and in caſe he do deny it, yet in the conſtruction of the fundamentall law and conſtitution of this Kingdom, he is conceived to grant it, ſupproſing the head not to be ſo unnaturall to the body that hath choſen it for good and not for evill.</p>
            <p>But it will be anſwered, where is the Kings Negative Voice if the Parliament may proceed without his conſent? I anſwer. That there is no known nor written law that gives him any; and things of that nature are willingly beleeved till they be abuſed, or with too much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence claimed. That his Majeſty hath fundamentally a right of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the enacting of laws is true, which (as aforeſaid) is part of that honourable truſt conſtituted in him: And that this royall aſcent is an act of honoer and not of abſolute and negative power orprerogative, appeares by theſe following reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by his oath at the Coronation mentioned in one of the Parliaments Declarations where he doth or ſhould ſweare to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and grant all ſuch good lawes as his people <hi>ſhall chooſe</hi> to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, not <hi>hath choſen,</hi> for firſt, The word <hi>concedis</hi> in that oath were then unneceſſary, the lawes formerly enacted being allready granted by foregoing Kings, and ſo they need no more <hi>conceſſion</hi> or confirmation, elſe we muſt run upon this ſhelfe that all our laws die with the old King, and receive their being a new, by the new Kings conſent. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Hereby the firſt and ſecond clauſe in that interrogatory, <hi>viz. Concedis iuſtas leges &amp; permittas prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gendas,</hi> are confounded and doe but <hi>idem repetere;</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Quas vulgus elegerit</hi> implies onely the act of the people in a disjunctive ſence from the act or conſent of the King, but laws allready made have more then <hi>quas vulgus elegerit,</hi> they have alſo the royall conſent too, ſo that that phraſe cannot meane them wherein the act or conſent of the King is allready involved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the practiſe of requiring the royall aſcent even unto thoſe very acts of ſubſidies which are granted to himſelfe and for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123813:6"/>his owne uſe, which it is ſuppoſed he will accept of, and yet <hi>Honoris gratia</hi> is his roiall aſcent craved and contributed thereunto.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the Kings not ſitting in Parliament to debate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult lawes, nor are they at all offered him by the Parliament to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of, but to conſent to, which yet are tranſmitted from one houſe to another, as well to conſult as conſent to, ſhewing thereby he hath no part in the conſultory part of them (for that it belongs onely to the people in Parliament to diſcerne and conſult their own good,) but he comes onely at the time of enacting, bringing his Royall Authority with him, as it were to ſet the ſeale thereof to the Indenture allready prepared by the people, for the King is head of the Parliament in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his authority, not in regard of his reaſon or judgement, as if it were to be oppoſed to the reaſon or judgement of both houſes (which is the reaſon both of King and Kingdome) and therefore do they as conſult ſo alſo interpret lawes without him, ſuppoſing him to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon repleniſhed with honour and royall authority not ſkilled in lawes, nor to receive information either of law or councell in Parliamentary affaires from any, ſaving from that ſupreame court and higheſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the King and Kingdome, which admits no counterpoize, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intruſted both as the wiſeſt Councell and juſteſt judicature.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, either the choiſe of the people in Parliament is to be the ground and rule of the Kings aſſent, or nothing but his pleaſure, and ſo all Bills though never ſo neceſſary for publique good and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and after never ſo much paines and conſultation of both houſes may be reiected, and ſo they made meere cyphers, and we brought to that paſſe, as either to have no lawes, or ſuch onely as come immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the King (who oft is a man of pleaſure, and little ſéene in publicke affaires, to be able to judge) and ſo the Kingdomes great councell muſt be ſubordinated either to his meere will, and then what difference between a free Monarchy, and an abſolvte, ſaving that the one rules without Councell, and the other againſt it, or at the beſt but to a cabinet councell conſiſting commonly of men of private intereſts, but certainly of no publicke truſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But if the King muſt conſent to ſuch laws as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall chuſe <hi>eo nomine,</hi> they may then propound unreaſonable things to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, as to conſent to his own depoſing, or to the leſſning his own revenew, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So that the iſſue is, whether it be fitter to truſt the wiſdome and integrity of our Parliament, or the will and pleaſure of the King in this caſe of ſo great and publicke concernment. In a word,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123813:6"/>the King being made the fountaine of juſtice and protection to his people by the fundementall lawes or conſtitution of this Kingdome, he is therefore to give life to ſuch acts and things as tend thereunto, which acts depend not upon his pleaſure, but though they are to receive their greater vigour from him, yet are they not to be ſuſpended at pleaſure by him, for that which at firſt was intended by the kingdome: for an honourable way of ſubſiſtence and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration muſt not be wreſted contrary to the nature of this Polity, (which is a free and mixt Monarchy and not an abſolute) to its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and confuſion, ſo that in caſe the King in his perſon ſhould decline his duty, the King in his courts are bound to performe it, where his authority properly reſides, for if he refuſe that honour which the republicke by its fundamentall conſtitution hath conferred upon him, and will not put forth the acts of it, for the end it was given him, <hi>viz.</hi> for the juſtice and ſafety of his people, this hinders not but that they who have as fundamentally reſerved a power of being &amp; wellbeing in their own handes by the concurrence of Parliamentary authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the royall dignity, may thereby provide for their own ſubſiſtence, wherein is acted the Kings juridicall authority though his perſonall pleaſure be withheld, for his legall and juridicall power is included and ſuppoſed in the very being, and conſequently in the acts of Courts of juſtice, whoſe being he may as well ſuſpend as their power of acting, for that without this is but a cypher, and therefore neither their being nor their acting ſo depend upon him, as not to be able to act and execute common juſtice and protection without him, in caſe he deny to act with them, and yet both ſo depend upon him, as that he is bound both in duty and honour, by the conſtitution of this polity to act in them and they from him, ſo that (according to that axiome in law) <hi>the King can doe no wrong,</hi> becauſe his iuridicall power and authority is allwayes to controle his perſonall miſcarriages.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123813:7"/>
            <head>Se Defendendo.</head>
            <p>GOd and nature hath ordained Government for the preſervation of the governed. This is a truth ſo undeniable, as that none will gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it, ſaving in practice, which therefore being taken for granted, it muſt needs follow that to what end Government was ordained, it muſt bee maintained, for that it is not in the power of particular perſons or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities of men to depart with ſelfe preſervation by any covenant whatſoever, nor ought it to bee exacted by any ſuperiours from their inferiours, either by oath or edict, becauſe neither oathes nor ſtatutes are obligatory further then they agree with the righteous Laws of God and nature; further then ſo they ought neither to be made nor kept.</p>
            <p>Let it be ſuppoſed then for argument ſake, that the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdom, is in the power of the King, yet now as the caſe ſtands it is lawfull for the Parliament to reaſſume it, becauſe though they paſſed it into his hands, for the peoples preſervation, yet it was never intended that by it he might compaſſe their deſtruction, contrary to the Law of nature; whereby every man, yea every thing is bound to preſerve it ſelfe. And thuſmuch in effect is confeſſed at unawares, by the Author of the Reply to the Anſwer of the London Petition: who affirmeth, ſaying <hi>The King is inveſted with the ſole power of Training, Arraying, and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering,</hi> and then gives the reaſon, <hi>becauſe it is moſt conſonant to reaſon, as well as grounded on Law, That he wich is bound to protect, ſhould be able to compaſſe that end.</hi> Which reaſon overthrows both his poſition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.
<list>
                  <item>1. His poſition, for this is no reaſon why the ſole power of the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould be in the hands of the King; <hi>becauſe he is bound to protect,</hi> except he were bound ſolely to protect, that is, without the counſel and advice of Parliament: but it hath beene reſolved that He is not ſole judge of neceſſity, and therefore not ſole protector againſt it, but together with His Parliament, who conſequently ſhares in the power of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. It overthrows His intention, which is ſo to put the power of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> into the hands of the King, as to enable him to do what he wil with it, whenas yet he himſelf cannot but affirm, it is his to protect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for hat when he ceaſeth to uſe it to its end, it ceaſeth to be in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, or elſe let the man ſpeake plain, and ſay, it is His to deſtroy as well as to protect.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But the <hi>Militia</hi> is paſſed to the King, abſolutely without any condition of revocation expreſſed, or of limitation to circumſcribe the uſe whereunto it ought to be imployed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Laws of God and nature, neither are nor need to be expreſſed in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123813:7"/>contracts or edicts, for they are ever ſuppoſed to be ſupreme to humane ordinances, and to chalenge obedience in the firſt place, and other Laws ſo far onely as they are conſonant to them, though theſe laws be further backed with Oathes and Proteſtations: As for inſtance, I give a man a ſword, and ſweare I will never take it from him; yet if he actually aſſault me, or it manifeſtly appeare he intends to cut my throat, or take my purſe with it, I may lawfully poſſeſſe my ſelfe of it again if opportunity ſerve, becauſe in ſuch agreements betwixt man &amp; man, the laws of nature nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are nor can be exempted, but are neceſſarily implyed, ſtill to be of force, becauſe no bonds can lawfully invalid them, and <hi>id ſolum poſſumus quod jure poſſumus.</hi> But it may be asked how it appeares that the King intends to imploy the <hi>Militia</hi> to the deſtruction of his people. Why firſt becauſe He hath refuſed to hearken to the wholſome counſel of His Parliament, the repreſentative body, and the higheſt Court and Counſel of the Kingdom. 2 Becauſe, <hi>è contrario,</hi> he hearkens to the councels of notorious Papiſts and Malignants, men engaged againſt the publike good and welfare of this Kingdome, in a diametrall oppoſition, ſo that if they periſh it proſpereth, and if it proſper they periſh. 3. Becauſe hee hath had a deepe hand in contriving and plotting the ruine and extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament, by ſecret and open violence, and in them of the whole Kingdome of whom they are the Epitome, and as the King is the head, ſo they are the heart. But further it may be replied, that the King hath promiſed to maintain Parliaments and governe by Law. <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is ſo far as he knowes his own heart, and as he can be maſter of himſelfe: He ſware the ſame at His Coronation, and promiſed as much when he granted the Petition of Right, but how they have beene kept God knowes, and we are not ignorant. It may be His Majeſty may meane as he ſpeakes, but
<list>
                  <item>1. Temptations may change his minde, as it hath done too often, and as it did his that ſaid to the Prophet, Is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant a dog that he ſhould do ſuch things? and yet did them. The welfare of Kingdomes is not to be founded upon bare ſpontaneous promiſes, but reall contracts.</item>
                  <item>2. He himſelfe ſayes, he himſelfe is not skild in the Laws, and we have found it true, ſo that he muſt take information of them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome body from his Parliament (that is his people that made them) he wil not, and are any fitter to be Judges of the Law, then the higheſt Court; if they may be Judges that are delinquents to the Law, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants againſt it, and have beene grievous oppreſſors of the People, even againſt the known Laws (ſo much cried up) we are like to have juſt Judges and righteous Lawyers.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſ.</hi> If the <hi>Militia</hi> be ſo abſolutely the Kings, as that all power of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123813:8"/>defence and preſervation of our ſelves and our rights be taken from us, to what purpoſe do we ſtrive for liberty &amp; property, and laws to confirm them? theſe are but imaginary things, if they have no hedg to fence them; If the <hi>Militia</hi> be for the King, let us burne the Statutes we have already, and ſave a labour of making more. No man would thinke it a good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to buy land, and when he hath paid his money to have it in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the ſeller, to take it from him by his ſword.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> It is true that Kings are tied by oath, and legall contracts, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne by Laws, and to maintain liberty and property to their people, which puts them under an obligation of conſcience to God, ſo that they are reſponſible to him for the breach of fidelity and duty, but not to the people who may minde them of their duty, but not compell them to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Objection hath two parts, Firſt, That Kings are onely reſponſible to God. 2. That Subjects muſt ſuffer, wrong, but not by force maintain their right. To the firſt I anſwer. That if Kings be ſolely anſwerable to God, then contracts are in vaine, for they ſhall anſwer for all their arbitrary and unjuſt tyrannie over their people, though there were no contracts. That which makes us happier then other Nations, ſure is not this, that the King for the breach of his duty hath more to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at the day of judgement then other Kings have, if that bee all wee have ſmall cauſe to joy in our priviledges, they are neither worth the blood that hath been ſhed for them, nor the money that hath beene paid for them. Secondly, Government muſt be conſidered under a twofold notion, divine and humane. The <hi>Genus</hi> which is government it ſelfe is divine, ſo that people are abſolutely bound to have government, but not bound to have an abſolute government, for the <hi>ſpecies</hi> or the <hi>modus guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi</hi> is humane, and therefore the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Be ſubject to every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man,</hi> that is, to every ſuch kinde of Government as your lot falls to be under, by the conſtitution of the Common-wealth you live in. Now Government being thus of a mixt nature, the Ordinance both of God and man, it is not onely ſubject to God but alſo to men, to be regulated, amended, and maintained by the people: for as it is Gods Ordinance for their good, ſo doth he give them liberty to provide it bee not abuſed to their hurt, ſo that when God ſhall put an opportunity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hands, they ought to improve it to the ſetting of government up right, or the keeping of it ſo from apparent violations. There was a time when both Government and the manner of governing belonged to God, to wit, amongſt the Iſraelites, for to that people he was both a God of moralls and politiks, and therefore he tooke it ſo ill for them to uſurpe upon his right, as to deſire to change their government from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123813:8"/>Judges to Kings, but this was a peculiar right he aſſumed over that particular people onely. To the ſecond I anſwer thus. Every Subject taken <hi>diviſim,</hi> and apart from the whole, is to ſuffer under abuſed autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to obey paſſively, rather then to breake union or cauſe confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no Subject is bound to ſuffer by that which is not authority, as is the will of the Magiſtrate: If a Court of Juſtice ſhould unjuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne a man, he is patiently to undergoe it, but if a Judge or the King himſelfe ſhould violently ſet upon him to kill him, he may defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; for the Ordinance of God and man both, is affixed to the office, and not unto the perſon, to the authority and not unto the will, ſo that the perſon acting out of office, and by his will may be reſiſted, though the ordinance may not. But the repreſentative body of the Common-wealth, (which is all men conjunctim) they may not onely oppoſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and his will, but even the office and authority it ſelfe when abuſed, and are bound to it both in conſcience to God when he gives them op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and in diſcharging of their truſt to them that imployed them. For firſt God calls to have the wicked removed from the Throne, and whom doth he call upon to doe it but upon the people (in caſe the King will not) or their truſtees, for as he hath originally founded all authority in the people, ſo he expects a diſcharge of it from them for his glory, &amp; the publike weale, which are the ends of Government, from which God and nature hath ordained it. Secondly, In diſcharge of their truſt for the whole, for order ſake, making them their repreſentative actors, and putting that univerſall and popular authority, that is in the body of the people, and which (for the publike good and preſervation) is above every man and all Laws, into their hands, they may expect and chalenge them by vertue of their ſtewardſhip, to provide for their ſafety and well being, againſt whomſoever ſhall oppoſe it, no one being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, and therefore ought not that univerſall power, which by way of truſt is conveyed over to the Parliament, be betrayed into the hands of any by admitting or allowing any authority to be ſuperiour, by tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting abuſes and uſurpations, as if they had not power to regulate them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
